So we start today on י"ז עמוד ב', Yod Zayin Amud Bet,
the משנה Mishnah
about 10 lines from bottom. Let's take a look.
בית שמאי אומרים. Beit Shammai Omrim. So now we are done with
a good few דפים Dapim dealing with the 18 things of בית
שמאי בית הלל Beit Shammai Beit Hillel that had almost nothing to
do with שבת, Shabbos, mostly with תרומה וטהרה. Terumah u-Teharah. And now
we are back to שבת. Shabbos. And now we have a series
of debates of בית שמאי בית הלל. Beit Shammai Beit Hillel. So
I should just mention that the רמב"ם Rambam reading through the ירושלמי,
Yerushalmi, the בבלי Bavli seems to see that the 18 things were
things they debated and then agreed upon, sort of conflated all into
one list. The ירושלמי Yerushalmi said there were three lists and the
רמב"ם Rambam actually says that these next debates of בית שמאי בית
הלל Beit Shammai Beit Hillel were a third list of 18 things
which remained the debate of בית שמאי בית הלל. Beit Shammai Beit
Hillel. So anyway let's take a look. We'll now have some debates
of שמאי והלל Shammai ve-Hillel until the end of the פרק Perek
which deals with שבת. Shabbos. בית שמאי אומרים אין שורין דיו וסמנים
וכרשינין אלא כדי שישורו מבעוד יום. Beit Shammai Omrim ein shorin deyo
ve-sammanim ve-karshinin ela kedei she-yishoru mi-be'od yom. You do not seep ink,
דיו, deyo, I mean whatever it would be the gall or the
things that they would use to make דיו, deyo, and various types
of also dyes and כרשינין karshinin which would be a food that
they would feed to animals. What is it called? Vetch. Vetch, there
you go. Anyway what they would do is that they would sink
it in
they would submerge it in water and you know that for it
would dye the water, it would turn the water into דיו, deyo,
it would absorb it into this vetch. Anyway, so you would do
this and you have to do this if you're going to do
this ערב שבת, Erev Shabbos, you can only do it אלא כדי
שישורו מבעוד יום, ela kedei she-yishoru mi-be'od yom, only if they can
absorb their water or that they can be completely sort of dissolved
into the water from the day before.
ובית הלל מתירים. U-Veit Hillel mattirin. בית הלל Beit Hillel allows. So
what we are going to see is a series of things that
בית שמאי Beit Shammai will only allow you to do beforehand if
it can get done before שבת Shabbos begins. You can't start something
before that will continue on שבת. Shabbos. Now obviously you can't take
this to an extreme because then they would never let you put
up food ערב שבת Erev Shabbos to cook on שבת. Shabbos. But
we'll have to figure out what the distinctions are and what the
reason for this is. And maybe I should say just right at
the outset that there are two possible explanations for what this is
about. One is a concern that one explanation is that it's a
type of a standard rabbinic concern that if you start it before
שבת Shabbos and it continues on שבת Shabbos then you wind up
coming to do it on שבת Shabbos itself. You know or either
to lead to you doing it or just it doesn't look good.
It looks like you're doing it on שבת Shabbos because it's happening
on שבת Shabbos for you. Again you'll have to figure out why
you can put up food and why you can keep candles lit
why it doesn't become sort of like the Karaites or something. So
that's one issue. Or like the what do you call it, like
the צדוקים. Tzadukim. But the other possibility is something that the גמרא
Gemara calls שביתת כלים. Shevitat Kelim. You have to let your animals
rest and your servants rest and your slaves rest so maybe you
have to also let your vessels rest and your vessels should not
be doing work on שבת. Shabbos. Okay so with all of these
you have to understand what are the exceptions but these are two
ways to understand בית שמאי, Beit Shammai, either a classic rabbinic concern
or maybe even something biblical. Alright. Now בית הלל Beit Hillel allows
it. So now we're going to have a whole list of things
which are pretty parallel to this. בית שמאי אומרים אין נותנין אונין
של פשתן לתוך
התנור אלא כדי שיהבילו מבעוד יום. Beit Shammai Omrim ein notnin unnin
shel pishtan le-tokh ha-tannur ela kedei she-yahavilu mi-be'od yom. You can only
put these sort of bundles of flax into an oven from the
day before only if they have time that they should heat up
from the day before. What you're trying to do to them is
like turn them white. This is a process of making I guess
linen out of flax and you put them into an oven and
they heat up and they turn white and it has to be
done from the day before.
Okay now it says בית שמאי אומרים, Beit Shammai Omrim, I would
did this, okay. ולא את הצמר ליורה אלא כדי שיקלוט העין. Ve-lo
et ha-tzemer le-yoreh ela kedei she-yiklot ha-ayin. And you can't put wool
into a vat of
dye only if it can absorb the dye from the day before.
ובית הלל מתירים. U-Veit Hillel mattirin. בית הלל Beit Hillel says okay.
בית שמאי אומרים אין פורסין מצודות חיה ועוף ודגים אלא כדי שיצודו
מבעוד יום. Beit Shammai Omrim ein porsin metzudot chayah ve-of ve-dagim ela
kedei she-yitzodu mi-be'od yom. You can only lay traps for wild animals
and birds and fish on ערב שבת Erev Shabbos if they can
get caught from the day before. ובית הלל מתירים. U-Veit Hillel mattirin.
בית הלל Beit Hillel allows. Now this is different from the rest
because you don't know you're going to trap animals. So one way
of reading this is only if there was sufficient time that in
theory they could have been caught. But that doesn't really explain it
because nevertheless on שבת Shabbos an animal might be getting caught in
your trap.
So תוספות Tosafot says well maybe we're talking about a circumstance where
it's very very easily caught and you know they'll be caught. I
mean I don't know when you could ever be so lucky to
put out a net and know something is going to get caught
in a certain amount of time. But anyway that's a little bit
strange because it doesn't seem from the simple sense of it that
you know it'll take place from the day before. בית שמאי אומרים
אין... Beit Shammai Omrim ein... now those were things where you set
up the whole mechanism and it finished by itself. Now you're going
to talk about involving a נכרי. Nokhri. בית שמאי אומרים אין מוכרין
לנכרי. Beit Shammai Omrim ein mokhrin le-Nokhri. You can't sell products to
a non-Jew, ואין טוענין עמו VeEin Toanin Imo and you can't load
up his donkey with him, ואין מגביהין עליו VeEin Magbihin Alav and
you can't even load it up on his back, אלא כדי שיגיע
למקום קרוב. Ela Kedei SheYagia LeMakom Karov. You have to be able
to get to a nearby place which is his home. ובית הלל
מתירין. UBeit Hillel Matirin. And this is quite different because here you
sold to the non-Jew and then you're out of the picture. You're
not even asked to do something for you. So this clearly is
a question about appearances. Here's this non-Jew, he's in your house, you
sell him something, you load it up on his donkey, you load
it up on his back, he walks out, and people, it looks
like you're maybe sending him to do something for you. Maybe you're
loading him up with grain to sell for you in the neighboring
town. But that's not what happened. What actually happened was he bought
the grain from you. So this clearly is an issue of appearances.
It's no longer your grain, it's not your donkey, it's the non-Jew,
and nevertheless Beit Shammai says you can't do it until he gets
home from the day before, so it should not look like למקום
קרוב. LeMakom Karov. Well, it depends what it means. If you look
at רש"י, Rashi, he says שיגיע למקום קרוב שהמקום קרוב שיוליכנו שם
מבעוד יום. SheYagia LeMakom Karov SheHaMakom Karov SheYolichenu Sham Mibe'od Yom.
That means where he is going, you're right, not his home necessarily,
but where he's going has to be close enough that he would
get there. There's a question of exactly how close.
ובית הלל מתירין
UBeit Hillel Matirin too, right?
What, if it looks bad?
Well, if it's a Jew, he's obviously you're assuming he's going to
get done before Shabbat. If not, it'll be like לפני עיוור. Lifnei
Iver. ובית הלל מתירין. UBeit Hillel Matirin. Beit Hillel would allow. בית
שמאי אומרים אין נותנין עורות לעבדן ולא כלים לכובס נוכרי אלא כדי
שיעשו מבעוד יום. Beit Shammai Omrim Ein Notnin Orot Le'Abdan Velo Kelim
LeKhoves Nochri Ela Kedei SheYe'asu Mibe'od Yom. Similarly,
now this actually becomes a question where you understand where it is
a little bit more questionable why Beit Hillel allows it, and this
is very relevant להלכה. LeHalakha. Beit Shammai says you cannot give your
leather to a tanner, assuming again a non-Jew, or your clothes to
a cleaner, a non-Jewish cleaner, only if they have time to get
done from the day before. So you can't drop off your laundry
before Shabbat, or you can't drop off your car at the mechanic's
before Shabbat unless he has time to finish it before it gets
Shabbat. ובית הלל מתירין. UBeit Hillel Matirin. Beit Hillel allows. Now here
it's really a little bit more questionable why Beit Hillel allows it,
right? Because here he is, he is doing your laundry, he might
be doing your laundry, he will according to Beit Hillel, he will
be doing your laundry on Shabbat. He will be working on your
car on Shabbat. It's not like the non-Jew is taking his own
stuff home. Here it seems to be more than appearances, and nevertheless
Beit Hillel allows it. So we will have to see why that
is. ובית הלל מתירין עם השמש. UBeit Hillel Matirin Im HaShemesh. Beit
Hillel allows this even if you do it anytime right before sunset.
אמר רבן שמעון בן גמליאל, Amar Rabban Shimon Ben Gamliel, נוהגים היו
בית אבא. Nohegin Hayu Beit Abba. My father's house, Rabban Shimon Ben
Gamliel, remember, was from the house of the נשיא. Nasi. So we
used to so in my father's house, Rabban Gamliel's house, we used
to שהיו נותנים כלי לבן לכובס נוכרי שלושה ימים קודם לשבת. SheHayu
Notnim Klei Lavan LeKhoves Nochri Shlosha Yamim Kodem LeShabbat. We would give
our white garments, which apparently took extra time to get really clean.
Now it's like easier to do whites, just throw in bleach, anyway,
I guess if you really wanted white to look white, it took
a lot of time. So we gave it to the non-Jew three
days before Shabbat so he'd have plenty of time to get it
done by Shabbat.
Seeming to be in the Beit Shammai mode. ושווים אלו ואלו, VeShavin
Elu VeElu, both Beit Shammai and Beit Hillel do agree at least,
שטוענין קורת בית הבד ועגולי הגת. SheToanin Korat Beit HaBad VeAgulei HaGat.
There is some things you can do before Shabbat. You can load,
you can put the beam of the oil vat and
the circle of the wine vat, you can lower them down. What
they would do is they would press wine and press olives. We
discussed that a little bit yesterday. So you would trample on them
or whatever to start getting the wine or the juice flowing, and
then you would lower extremely heavy weights down upon them. Anytime, if
you've ever in Israel, you go to these archaeological sites, you always
see these ancient wine vats and ancient olive presses, and they would
use like huge stones or huge beams to put down, and the
weight would slowly press out the oil. So that you can do
ערב שבת Erev Shabbat even though over the course of Shabbat it's
squeezing out the oil and squeezing out the grape juice. So the
question is, why does Beit Shammai allow that? So we will take
a look at all about this in the גמרא. Gemara. So there's
going to be question number one: what's Beit Shammai's reason for being
strict? Number two: what are the things he allows, like these last
things in the משנה? Mishna? What's the most obvious thing that the
Gemara is going to ask is having lights on on Shabbat and
having your food cooking from ערב שבת? Erev Shabbat? And then בית
הלל Beit Hillel is going to be the interesting case, which actually
is practical הלכה Halakha about giving things to a non-Jew right before
Shabbat begins. Why is that allowed? So let's take a look at
what the Gemara says. Okay,
so the Gemara jumps right in to, before getting into the bigger
issues here, into the local issue of the ink. And it says
the following: מאן תנא נתינת מים לדיו זו היא שרייתן? Man Tana
Netinat Mayim LeDyo Zo Hi Shriyatan?
Who says putting water in with the ink, or whatever these are,
I think what were the things called that they made ink out
of? Gall, was it?
No, there were these little, does it say there in any of
your Englishes what they would make ink out of, what they would
put into the water? Next piece follows.
מן תנא דנתן מים לדיו זו
היא שרייתן?
Man tanna denatan mayim ladio
zu hi sheriyatan?
Who says putting water in with the ink or whatever these are
of? I think what were the things called that they made ink
out of? Gall, was it?
No, there was these little... does it say there in any of
your Englishes what they would make ink out of, what they would
put into the water to make ink? No. It's these whatever, some
certain type of a thing that would give the- that they'd absorb
it in water and it would turn into... to make ink? No,
it doesn't say? It just says ink? It just says that they
would soak it.
Yeah, anyway, there was something gall, gallnut, I forget, anyway, something, anyway,
maybe I'm confusing or something. Anyway, so what they would do is
they would soak it in water. So who says that
this זו היא שרייתן zu hi sheriyatan is its absorbing? Now, what
does it really mean by is its absorbing is that it's a
מלאכה. melacha. The assumption here is is that the things that בית
שמאי Beis Shammai do not allow you to do, do not allow
you to get started ערב שבת Erev Shabbos and continue on שבת,
Shabbos, are things that are מלאכה. melacha. Okay? So all these things
that we quoted before were מלאכה, melacha, like what for example? Putting
these, putting the flax in an oven, either that's a type of
a cooking, which is interesting, it's not food, or maybe it's a
type of a צביעה, tzvia, dyeing, like changing the color. Certainly the
putting of the wool into the dye-vat, that is a type of
a צביעה. tzvia. Capturing animals is צידה, tzeda, that's a מלאכה. melacha.
But what is the מלאכה melacha of putting this ink thing into
of this,
this material into water and turning it into ink? So let's take
a look. אמר רב יוסף, Amar Rav Yosef, רבי, Rebbi, it's רבי.
Rebbi. דתניא, Detanya, we taught in a ברייתא, Baraisa,
אחד נותן את הקמח ואחד נותן את המים. Echad nosein es hakemach
ve-echad nosein es hamayim. So the גמרא Gemara understands that the מלאכה
melacha here, like maybe you could have thought that the מלאכה melacha
was like a צביעה, tzvia, coloring, but you're really not coloring, I
mean what are you coloring? You're coloring the water. Normally when we
talk about coloring, dyeing, we're talking about dyeing some material, not about
dyeing water. So the גמרא Gemara understands that the מלאכה melacha you
would be doing here would actually be something you probably would never
have thought of, would be לישה, lisha, kneading. Because basically what's kneading?
Kneading is you put water together with flour, so you put something
that's tiny little pieces, you add water to them and you make
it some homogeneous mass. And then of course like you knead it
all together. So here the גמרא Gemara understands that somehow you have
these again I really wish I knew better how dye was made,
but you have these various
little like whatever they are,
like a things that grew, I don't know if they're vegetables or
whatever they are, some type of nut. Doesn't really say there anything
about how the dye is made? Very disappointing.
There are a lot of ways it's made, most common in Roman
times was based on carbon.
So what would they do? They would take like ashes or what
would they do?
Like some I guess some kind of charcoal,
and iron with combining it with iron oxide.
And then add what, water?
Deep black coloring substance manufactured by a reaction of iron salt with
tannic acid, extracted from gallnuts. Yeah.
Okay, it doesn't say what they would do, what the process would
be?
No.
All right, anyway, you obviously use גלס, galls, yes,
I thought it was galls.
They came about 1600 years ago, which would have been after the
משנה. Mishna.
Okay, so it wasn't galls. So anyway, so they would take
something and
they'd add water. So if you think about it, that's somewhat parallel
to how you make a dough. You have flour, little pieces, you
add water, it makes it into one type of homogeneous mass. Now,
that's and it can be more liquidy. I know, ink is more
liquidy, so it's loose, it's sort of more like a bake batter
than like a flour batter let's say. Anyway, the גמרא Gemara understands
that that could be a type of a לישה. lisha. Now, לישה
lisha is actually the kneading. Here you're just adding the water. So
this is the גמרא's Gemara question. So רבי, Rebbi, this is רבי.
Rebbi. דתניא, Detanya, we taught in a ברייתא, Baraisa, אחד נותן את
הקמח ואחד נותן את המים, Echad nosein es hakemach ve-echad nosein es
hamayim, one person adds flour and one person adds water. האחרון חייב,
Ha-acharon chayav, the one who added the water is חייב chayav for
making dough. דברי רבי, Divrei Rebbi, that's what רבי Rebbi said. רבי
יוסי אומר אינו חייב עד שיגבל. Rebbi Yosei omer eino chayav ad
she-iygabel. No, no, no, לישה lisha is not just adding the water
to the flour, you have to actually knead it. Only the kneading
is actually the making of flour. So it has to be רבי
Rebbi because you don't knead when you add the when you make
the ink, but you do add the water to some type of
like let's say ashes. אמר ליה אביי, Amar lei Abaye, so אביי
Abaye said, and so it has to be רבי Rebbi because according
to this is only a problem if you're actually doing a מלאכה,
melacha, we're assuming, if the מלאכה's melacha being done on שבת. Shabbos.
And there is a מלאכה melacha here.
אמר ליה אביי, Amar lei Abaye, ודילמא עד כאן לא קאמר רבי
יוסי אלא בקמח דבר גיבול הוא? vedilma ad kan lo ka-amar Rebbi
Yosei ela bekemach debar gibbul hu? Maybe רבי יוסי Rebbi Yosei who
says you have to knead and that's part of the idea of
לישה, lisha, that's only by flour where the normal way of making
flour is that after you add the water you knead it. אבל
דיו דלאו בר גיבול הוא, Aval dio delav bar gibbul hu, but
ink which is made by just the adding of the water and
that's not something that gets kneaded together, אימא לחייב, eima lechayav, maybe
you're חייב chayav even without kneading. לא סלקא דעתך, Lo salka datach,
no, that doesn't make sense. דתניא, Detanya, we taught in a ברייתא,
Baraisa, אחד נותן את האפר ואחד נותן את המים, Echad nosein es
ha-eifer ve-echad nosein es hamayim,
one person adds ashes and the other water. So here it's clear
the way you're making it, this seems to be clearly about ink,
is ashes and water. האחרון חייב, Ha-acharon chayav, דברי רבי. divrei Rebbi.
רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה אומר עד שיגבל. Rebbi Yosei berabbi Yehuda omer
ad she-iygabel. So you see even with this case of ashes and
water we're talking about only with kneading. And even though it's not
the normal thing according to רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה Rebbi Yosi b'Rebbi
Yehuda and only the שיטה shita of רבי. Rebbi. So גמרא Gemara
says no, דילמא מאי אפר עפר. dilma mai efer aphar. Maybe when
it says אפר, efer, it doesn't mean ashes, it means dirt. Okay,
because sometimes although they mean different things, sometimes they are used a
little interchangeably. And if it means dirt, therefore what? So maybe if
you are making, when would you add water to dirt? Well kids
would do it if they're in the, if they're in, right, if
they're in the sandbox. But if you're trying to make like clay
or, you know, or some type of a, you know, plaster or
whatever exactly. So that type of a thing you would add the
water and then you actually would knead it in order to make,
you know, a good type of a clay. So therefore that's why
you need to, to knead it. So the גמרא Gemara says עפר
דבר גיבול הוא, aphar debar gibul hu, it is something that gets
kneaded. גמרא Gemara says one minute, והתניא אפר והתניא עפר. vehatanya efer
vehatanya aphar.
One minute, we have two ברייתות, braisos, one says אפר efer and
one says עפר. aphar. So clearly one is talking about ashes and
one is talking about dirt. And even when we're talking about ashes,
רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה Rebbi Yosi b'Rebbi Yehuda says you need to,
you need to knead it. So anyway, so you see even by
ashes there's the debate. So גמרא Gemara says no, מידי גבי הדדי
תניא? midi gabei hadadi tanya? Who says that they were taught, they
were taught, you know, right next to each other? Meaning maybe they're
from different schools. If you look at רש"י, Rashi, רש"י Rashi says,
מידי גבי הדדי תנינהו, midi gabei hadadi taninhu, חדא תנא רבי חייא
וחדא תנא רבי אושעיא, chada tana Rebbi Chiya vechada tana Rebbi Oshaya,
וחד מנהון תנא לעפר ולשאר אפר, vechad minhon tana l'aphar u'l'shar efer,
meaning they come from different sources. You know, רבי חייא Rebbi Chiya
and רבי אושעיא Rebbi Oshaya are assumed to be the source of
ברייתות. braisos. So one came from the school of רבי חייא, Rebbi
Chiya, one came from the school of רבי אושעיא. Rebbi Oshaya. They
both mean dirt, but one said אפר efer but it really meant
עפר. aphar. Just because one says עפר aphar and one says אפר
efer doesn't mean אפר efer means, means something different. It only would
mean something different if they're coming from the same source. But if
they're coming from different sources, they could both mean the same. So
this becomes a very interesting question, which I'm not going to explore
now, but what are the parameters of the מלאכה melacha of לישה?
lisha? Because this actually is an issue. First of all, it's an
issue if kids are playing in the sandbox and adding water. It's
also an issue if you are like, want to make like instant
oatmeal or something, you know, and you want to add water and
so on. And then there is the question about and then things
that normally do require, normally are stirred together. So instant oatmeal, normally
you don't just add the water, right, you do sort of like
stir it together. So then there's a question about like, so how
can you stir it together? Do you have to do it with
a שינוי, shinui, you know, and what type of a שינוי? shinui?
Anyway, so there are a lot of like practical applications of the
issues about לישה. lisha. It's not when something dissolves. There's no problem,
for example, about making instant coffee. It's about when the things are
tiny little separate things that all get sort of congealed into a
homogeneous mass through the adding of liquid. Somebody once asked רב משה,
Reb Moshe, what about adding mayonnaise to tuna fish? Because the argument
was, was that, well first of all even tuna fish in normal
is already somewhat of a mass, it's not like separate pieces, but
the bigger argument is, is that the mayonnaise is more like a
glue. It's not like normally when you add the liquid, the liquid
creates some chemical change so that it transforms into one type of,
you know, mass. Here the mayonnaise is just causing separate pieces to
stick together, but it's not actually transforming it. So it makes a
lot of sense you should be able to do it. רב משה
Reb Moshe said, was said you shouldn't do it actually. So, although
there's a pretty good logic to do it. So anyway, so I
really hear the סברא sevara that it should be totally מותר, mutar,
but when we make a tuna fish sandwich in my house on
שבת, Shabbos, we sort of, we do it like, you know, smear
the mayonnaise on the bread rather than mixing it into it, being
מחמיר machmir for that רב משה. Reb Moshe. Anyway, there are some
interesting applications about לישה lisha and this question about בר גיבול bar
gibul is an important one. Things that are not normally kneaded, is
it that it's a problem even earlier on, which is what רבי
Rebbi says, or is it the opposite? Is it that it's harder
to transgress? תוספות Tosafot points out, if there's רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה
Rebbi Yosi b'Rebbi Yehuda and תוספות Tosafot quotes other גמרות Gemaras that
actually say that if you don't normally do גיבול, gibul, you wouldn't
transgress. So, that question about when you don't normally knead, are you
transgressing sooner or later is an important issue. So this is a
very relevant להלכה. l'halacha.
I was just wondering what the whole question of the גמרא Gemara
was. They say
מאן תנא דתנן המים והדיו וכו', man tana detnan hamayim vehadiyo v'chu,
אתיא כבית שמאי. atya k'Beit Shammai.
No, no, no, no, no. There's one question which is, is it
אסור assur to have things start ערב שבת? Erev Shabbos? That's clearly
בית שמאי. Beit Shammai. But the גמרא Gemara is assuming,
although it hasn't said it, but it's assuming the only things that
בית שמאי Beit Shammai says you can't start ערב שבת Erev Shabbos
are things that when they're done on שבת Shabbos would be a
מלאכה. melacha. And therefore, where do we know that this, that this
is a מלאכה? melacha? Now obviously, yes, implicitly בית שמאי Beit Shammai
is saying that position, but we want to be able to identify
it with what we know our debate, our positions about this מלאכה,
melacha, right?
Or do they assume that the, literally everyone is a מלאכה, melacha,
maybe they're just, so you don't want to...
I understand. So that's a good question. The גמרא, Gemara, you are
correct and we will continue to see that the גמרא Gemara is
working with the assumption that the things we forbid ערב שבת, Erev
Shabbos, that בית שמאי Beit Shammai forbids, are things that will be
a מלאכה melacha once, once you know, that if you were to
do it on שבת Shabbos would be a מלאכה. melacha. Okay? But
we will see that. Okay, but that is clearly the assumption of
the גמרא. Gemara. Now, now we get to the bigger theme, and
we get to the bigger theme by quoting a ברייתא braisa that
has other things about doing them ערב שבת, Erev Shabbos, although the
ברייתא braisa is not clear whether it is בית שמאי Beit Shammai
or בית הלל. Beit Hillel. Let's take a look. תנו רבנן, tanu
rabanan, פותקין מים לגינה. potkin mayim l'gina. ערב שבת עם חשכה. erev
Shabbos im chasheicha.
You can open up
a water like from some irrigation funnel or whatever into your garden
ערב erev Shabbos right before it gets dark. So, you know, you
can turn on the sprinklers would basically be what we would say.
Okay. וממלאה והולכת כל היום כולו. umemalei veholeches kol hayom kulo. And
it could be filling up the entire day, the entire I don't
know what it means to be filling up the garden with water,
but you know, continuing water to be irrigated in the garden. He
means like flooding plains. Maybe, yeah, I don't know. ומניחין מוגמר תחת
הכלים umenichin mugmar tachas hakeilim and you can put a burning incense
under כלים, keilim, כלים keilim here seems to mean clothes. ומתגמר והולך
כל היום כולו umisgamer veholeich kol hayom kulo because what they would
do is, you know, they didn't have so they they didn't have
such good deodorants so what they would do is they would they
would get they would burn incense over their clothes and their clothes
would absorb the aroma of the incense and that would be help
in terms of their smells and so on. So you could do
that ערב שבת erev Shabbos and the clothes would continue to absorb
the smoke of the incense, the smell of the incense, the entire
day. מניחין גופרית תחת הכלים, menichin gofris tachas hakeilim, you could burn
type of sulfur underneath vessels and this would here be רשי Rashi
says is like silver vessels. ומתגפרין והולכין כל השבת כולה umisgafrin veholchin
kol hashabbos kulo and they could go ahead and get the like
the black through the entire שבת. Shabbos. Apparently רשי Rashi says that
you would have designs on silver vessels and by burning this sulfur
underneath it, it would absorb some of the blackness, the designs would
stand out. At least that's how רשי Rashi is explaining it. Anyway,
so a similar type of idea. ומניחין קילור על גבי העין umenichin
kilor al gabei ha'ayin and you can put some type of a
salve on the eye, ואיספלנית על גבי מכה ve'isplanis al gabei makah
and a type of also a like a a bandage but a
bandage with a, you know, with a medicine on it, right, with
some type of a salve. ומתרפאין והולכין כל היום כולו umisrapin veholchin
kol hayom kulo and they can go ahead and be healing the
entire day. אבל אין נותנין חטין לתוך הריחיים של מים. aval ein
nosnin chitin lesoch hareichayim shel mayim.
You cannot put your wheat into your water wheel
and then it's going to like you know in a water mill
I should say, אלא בכדי שיטחנו מבעוד יום. ela bichdei sheyitachnu mib'od
yom. It has to get done from the day before.
So the first obvious question is why is that different? And the
second question is, you know, what's the issue going on here? This
seems to be the position of בית הלל. Beis Hillel. He lets
you do all this stuff ערב שבת. erev Shabbos. The one exception
is the wheat in the water wheel. So מאי טעמא, mai ta'ama,
what's the reason? אמר רבה, amar Rabbah, מפני שמשמעת קול, mipnei shemashma'as
kol,
because it makes noise. Now why is making noise an issue? I'll
stop here for a second. So if you take a look at
רשי, Rashi, רשי Rashi says מפני שמשמעת קול, mipnei shemashma'as kol,
it's about ten lines before the lines get wide. ואוושא מילתא, ve'avsha
milsa, there's a like a lot of the matter is very sort
of publicized בשבת, beShabbos, ואיכא זילותא ve'ika zilusa
and it is a you know it's a degradation of שבת, Shabbos,
it makes it makes שבת Shabbos look you know
what's the better word for זילותא? zilusa? I don't know. Degradation. Anyway.
It profanes. Profaned. Degraded. Yeah, degradation. It's inappropriate for שבת. Shabbos. Now
this becomes an interesting question about משמיע קול. mashmi'a kol. There is
a ירושלמי Yerushalmi that says that makes it clear that there was
an idea for שבת Shabbos of quiet. That quiet per se was
a very big idea of שבת Shabbos and even there's one the
ירושלמי Yerushalmi tells a story about somebody that was knocking on the
door and some and one of the תנאים Tana'im said, "Who's being
מחלל שבת?" mechallel Shabbos? That just the sound of knocking on the
door, right, there was whole idea that שבת Shabbos a day of
rest meant a day of quiet.
That's why we stay in Pikesville every שבת. Shabbos.
There you go. What? That's right. Well, no, well, that could be
why you don't clap. That's not why the בבלי Bavli says you
don't clap. But but that could be for the ירושלמי Yerushalmi that
is that is an idea. That does not seem to be at
least the general approach of the בבלי. Bavli. And it does seem
to be here that there's still two ways of understanding it. One
is it's just a very loud noise. Like small noise, you know,
whatever, big noise that's not that's considered to be not שבת-דיק. Shabbos-dik.
But it could be a little bit more specific. And it could
be that the noise that's being made is the noise of a
running of a water mill. So of a you know, so that
makes it sound like on an experiential level that it seems like
business is being done on שבת, Shabbos, right? So if I were
to turn on, you know, my huge factory and the things would
be chugging and the smoke would be coming out, oh I did
it all ערב שבת, erev Shabbos, but the feeling on שבת Shabbos
is that work is being done on שבת. Shabbos. So that is
an like a question about what exactly are the parameters of this.
תוספות Tosafos has a question in the מסקנא, maskana, do we פוסק
pasken this concern of משמיע קול mashmi'a kol on שבת? Shabbos? So
there's a question. But if we do, then there's a question about
what are the parameters. Like for example, is there you know there's
a question about can you set your dishwasher on a timer so
that you know so that it's so that it runs on שבת?
Shabbos? And some people say you can't do it because it's משמיע
קול. mashmi'a kol. You know, and רב סולובייצ'יק Rav Soloveitchik there's stories
that he said it's not a problem at all.
So so what's the issue? You know, so the issue you know
if it's about how noisy it is, most of these dishwashers are
not too noisy. You know, if it's about that it feels seems
like מלאכה melacha is being done, you know, maybe it's a little
bit more of an issue, but even then the question is you
know it's all a question about like what norms we've accepted, you
know, when your שבת Shabbos clock... שבת shabbos clocks go on, you
know, switch on your lights, it doesn't like feel like a מלאכה's
melacha being done. You learn to accept that that's being done by
שבת shabbos clocks, and it's certainly not the same degree of noise
as like a watermill, which is an unusual, you know, really impacts
like the whole experience of the whole city. It seems like that
like מלאכה's melacha being done.
Comparison between dishwasher and watermill? Right.
Yeah. Yeah. So I mean I think that these do raise like,
you know, real like interesting questions because now we're getting into a
question about not just like it'll, you know, גזירה, gezeira, it will
lead to something, but at an experiential level how that influences the
experience of שבת shabbos even if nothing wrong is actually being done.
So that's how the גמרא Gemara explains the issue of the watermill.
There's a question if we פוסק pasken this idea of משמיע קול
להלכה mashmia kol lehalacha regardless. Yes?
I don't understand the watering of plants on שבת shabbos being permitted.
You're causing things to grow. The water may be germinating new plants.
You're growing things on שבת. shabbos.
Wait no no no, the watermill is just the water turning it.
In the first one, in the first example.
Yeah, because everything you did was... why can you put food on
the fire right before שבת? shabbos?
But but you can't plant a seed on שבת.
shabbos. You're watering it by watering it. But you're not watering it
on שבת. shabbos. You... whatever you did... same is putting the food
on the fire ערב שבת. erev shabbos. You put raw food on
the fire ערב שבת erev shabbos and it cooks on שבת. shabbos.
But it has to be cooked a certain...
No, no it doesn't. That's only... if you put on a טשולנט
cholent a minute before... no, no no no. That's only
the reason... certain degrees might be required is so that you don't
accidentally come and stir. But if you actually have a בלעך, blech,
it doesn't even... you know, it doesn't have to be. You can
put a טשולנט cholent on a minute before שבת. shabbos. You can
put stuff on the fire to cook on... why can you light
a candle ערב שבת? erev shabbos? It's burning on שבת. shabbos.
But plants you're creating a new life, a new plant thing on
שבת. shabbos.
But that's exactly the point. The only thing that is forbidden on
שבת shabbos is a מלאכה melacha on שבת. shabbos. Any act that's
your activity, it's your labor, it's not what you cause. You cannot
do an act of creating on שבת. shabbos. Your creative act was
done ערב שבת. erev shabbos. Now it's just running by itself. Look,
you're in בית שמאי's Beis Shammai camp then if you're bothered by
this. But this is what בית הלל Beis Hillel says. It all
does with what you do, your actual activity on שבת shabbos itself.
How do we light candles? It's the same thing. Same מלאכה, melacha,
making a fire. Your fire from ערב שבת erev shabbos is causing
a continued fire on שבת. shabbos. Okay, so that's exactly the position.
So let's see what the גמרא Gemara says. So this is the
one difference is the watermill. So now let's see what the גמרא
Gemara says.
Okay. אמר רב יוסף. Amar Rav Yosef. So רב יוסף Rav Yosef
said to רבא, Rava, who said that the only issue, that this
was basically not a... only a concern of the watermill, everything was
basically מותר. muttar. ואימא מר משום שביתת כלים? V'eima mar mishum shevisas
keilim? Why not say there's a problem,
this is the watermill issue, of making your vessels rest? Which seems
to be a big, possibly a big Shammai concern. דתניא דתנן בברייתא,
Detanya detnan babraisa, ובכל אשר אמרתי אליכם תשמרו, Uvechol asher amarti aleichem
tishamairu, everything I told you you should observe. And this comes after
saying you have to let your animals rest. So what's ובכל, uvechol,
everything, broadening the idea of things that have to rest? לרבות שביתת
כלים, Lerabbos shevisas keilim, that even your vessels have to rest on
שבת. shabbos. So... oh so that would be pretty amazing...
Yosef Shmuel, ושם אלהים אחרים לא תזכירו לא ישמע על פיך... v'shem
elohim acherim lo tazkiru lo yishama al picha...
No, the previous verse is about שבת. shabbos. Okay, so... so anyway,
אלא אמר רב יוסף משום שביתת כלים. Ella amar Rav Yosef: mishum
shevisas keilim. He thinks it's שביתת כלים. shevisas keilim.
Now that... שביתת כלים shevisas keilim could accept maybe בית שמאי's Beis
Shammai position in the משנה. Mishna. But בית הלל Beis Hillel says
everything is okay. So... so it would be one thing to say
this משנה Mishna was בית שמאי Beis Shammai and it's שביתת כלים.
shevisas keilim. But how do you say it's בית הלל, Beis Hillel,
presumably we're working here within a position we פוסק pasken within בית
הלל? Beis Hillel? And how is everything else allowed? So you gave
this huge answer of שביתת כלים, shevisas keilim, this created this big
new category just to answer the one case of the watermill. Now
you have to explain every single other case why it's allowed if
if there's this new idea of שביתת כלים. shevisas keilim. So he
says, והשתא דאמרת v'hasha demart לבית הלל l'Beis Hillel אית ליה is
שביתת כלים shevisas keilim דאורייתא, de'oraisa, now you're trying to say that
בית הלל Beis Hillel holds of שביתת כלים shevisas keilim because presumably
we're working within בית הלל, Beis Hillel, so how can you do
everything else in that ברייתא? braisa? גופרית ומוגמר מאי טעמא שרו? Gofnis
v'mugmar mai ta'ama sharu?
Why can you burn this like sulfur or the incense? משום דלא
קעביד מעשה, Mishum d'lo kavid ma'aseh, because they're not... you're not doing
an act but the כלים keilim aren't doing an act. Meaning you
have them in some type of a bowl and you have your
incense and you've got a little fire going, but the vessel is
passive. Okay, now we're going to say see, if we're trying
to say שביתת כלים shevisas keilim is to say that's the position
that makes everything אסור. assur. But if you're going to say שביתת
כלים shevisas keilim and all these things are מותר, muttar, then you're
have to define שביתת כלים shevisas keilim in a very narrow way.
So שביתת כלים shevisas keilim is only when the vessel is like
moving, is like you know there are movable parts to the vessel.
If it's just like a bowl and there's a fire underneath it,
then the bowl isn't doing anything so the bowl isn't doing a
מלאכה. melacha. Okay, the fire's doing a מלאכה, melacha, but that's not
a vessel, and the bowl isn't moving. that would not be שביתת
כלים. shvitas keilim. So that's how you explain the incense. So אונין
של פשתן, unnin shel pishtan, מאי טעמא שרו? mai ta'ama sharu? So
now we have to go back though and explain everything in the
Mishnah. All of a sudden, I mean, this makes things oh my
god so difficult. Beit Hillel holds שביתת כלים? shvitas keilim? How do
they allow everything they're allowing? So how do they allow the flax?
So same idea. So משום דלא עביד
מעשה mishum delo avid ma'aseh because you're just putting them in the
oven. Everything is stationary. As long as the vessel is stationary, isn't
moving, right now, so that's the way we could explain Beit Hillel
holds of it but in a very narrow case. What vessel is
moving? Well, the water wheel, the water mill. That is a moving
vessel. That is the vessel that has to rest. But all these
other things, everything is stationary.
What's the סברא sevara for שביתת כלים? shvitas keilim?
What's the סברא sevara for שביתת בהמתו? shvitas behemto? Well, what's there?
It says things you own have to rest. So you understand, things
you own have to rest. Okay.
The Torah sort of blew it in this like backhanded way from
ובכל. uv-chol. No, it's trying to get at something. I don't know.
I don't know. מאי טעמא? mai ta'ama? Okay, so now the Gemara
says like מאי טעמא שרו משום דלא עביד מעשה ומנח ניחא. mai
ta'ama sharu mishum delo avid ma'aseh u-manach neicha.
The, you know, the flax is stationary, the oven is stationary, no
vessel is moving. Alright, I got one for you. מצודות חיה ועוף
ודגים metzudos chayah v'of v'dagim that's doing an action. מאי טעמא שרו?
mai ta'ama sharu?
How about traps? Like traps, like you know if it's like one
of those bear traps it snaps or whatever, you know, something like
a twig moves up or whatever, pulls up the rope or however
it works. That's doing an action. Why is that allowed? So מאי
טעמא שרו? mai ta'ama sharu? התם נמי בלחי וקוקרי. hasam nami b'lechi
u-kukari.
That's a type of a trap where it's basically stationary. Rashi says
like you've got a hook which is a לחי. lechi. So if
the fish bites the hook, the hook didn't move, like the fish
bit into it. Like the trap itself didn't move, it was moved
by the fish. Or like a net. So also if it's a
type of a net, you know, the thing itself, the כלי kli
was relatively stationary. And so we're trying to explain שביתת כלים. shvitas
keilim. It's a very like weird corner we're painting ourselves into. Okay,
we're basically saying that as opposed to Beit Shammai who forbids all
these things, that could be based on שביתת כלים, shvitas keilim, to
get this one case of the water wheel, we're trying to say
that Beit Hillel says שביתת כלים shvitas keilim but only if the
כלי kli is actually, you know, actually moving. And that would be
the one case of the water wheel. Okay, so the Gemara says
what?
Not the noise.
Not the noise, right. He's saying why did you say it's about
the noise? Why don't we say that it's Beit Hillel and but
Beit Hillel himself holds of שביתת כלים? shvitas keilim? Now we're saying
as long as the vessel is actually doing some action and moving.
Okay, so all these cases that we had mentioned before, right, none
of them was the vessel actually moving. It was all stationary. The
one case would be the traps which we got out of and
the water wheel.
It's even like a dishwasher would be a problem because it's actually
moving.
Yeah, right, if that's a מלאכה, melacha, right. Yeah, like a sprinkler.
Yeah, although I said a sprinkler to contemporize it but it really
was more like you open up a pipe and it just flows
out. Right, that's a good point, Bo. Okay, so the Gemara says
okay, okay. והשתא דאמר רבי אושעיא אמר רבי אסי מאן תנא שביתת
כלים דאורייתא בית שמאי היא. v'hashta d'amar Rabi Oshaya amar Rabi Assi
man tanna shvitas keilim d'oraisa Beis Shammai hi. But one minute. We
have a Braita that says no, Beit Shammai is the one who
holds of שביתת כלים shvitas keilim which makes sense, not Beit Hillel.
So forget all of that. So Beit Shammai says all those stuff
was forbidden and that's because of שביתת כלים shvitas keilim and even
if it's not a moving vessel, even if it's stationary, if the
vessel is somehow being used in a מלאכה melacha even by being
stationary, that also is שביתת כלים. shvitas keilim. ולא בית הלל. v'lo
Beis Hillel. So now we'll say like this. לבית שמאי בין כעביד
מעשה בין דלא כעביד מעשה אסור. l'Beis Shammai bein ka-avid ma'aseh bein
d'lo ka-avid ma'aseh assur. Whether the vessel is physically acting and moving
or whether it's stationary, that's still שביתת כלים. shvitas keilim. לבית הלל.
l'Beis Hillel. According to Beit Hillel, אף על גב דקעביד מעשה שרי.
af al gav d'ka-avid ma'aseh shari. Even if it's moving, it's permissible
like the trap. And therefore how do we explain the case about
the what do you call it, about the water mill? Just like
we said before, because it makes noise. Okay, that would be the
end of it.
והשתא דאמרת. v'hashta d'amart. So that's one explanation of Beit Shammai, that
it's about שביתת כלים. shvitas keilim. Now Tosafot points out that before
the Gemara introduced שביתת כלים, shvitas keilim, presumably you had another way
of understanding what was going on and that's the point I told
you, that the issue of Beit Shammai is just simply that it
doesn't look good. It looks like you're doing מלאכה melacha on Shabbat,
has nothing to do with שביתת כלים, shvitas keilim, and that's much
more consistent with Beit Shammai's position about giving stuff to the non-Jew,
right, that you start something before Shabbat, it looks like you're doing
it on Shabbat, it doesn't matter if it's your vessel, it doesn't
matter if it's something you sold to a non-Jew, and it's a
more general rabbinic thing. So that's one approach to Beit Shammai. This
approach is no, it's a biblical issue and it's about your vessels
not working on Shabbat the same way your animals can't work. Either
way we don't פוסקין poskin it, but two very different approaches for
Beit Shammai.
Why'd you say it doesn't look good?
It looks like you're doing a מלאכה. melacha.
How does it look like I'm doing a מלאכה melacha if a
non-Jewish cleaner is cleaning? How would they know it's mine?
No, so it looks like you told him to do it. Right,
it looks like he's your שליח. shaliach. Okay, so not necessarily what,
so it looks like you're involved in a מלאכה, melacha, whether you're
doing it directly or you're involved in a מלאכה. melacha. והשתא דאמרת
לבית שמאי אף על גב דלא עביד מעשה אסור. v'hashta d'amart l'Beis
Shammai af al gav d'lo avid ma'aseh assur. Now according to Beit
Shammai even if it's not doing something is forbidden. אי הכי מוגמר
וגופרית מאי טעמא שרו בית שמאי. Ee hachi mugmar vegofris mai ta'ama
sharu Beit Shammai. So we are still now assuming though, right, that
that this תוספתא Tosefta which is a bit bizarre. We have one
question which is what's the debate of בית שמאי בית הלל שביתת
כלים. Beit Shammai Beit Hillel shvisas kelim. We have another question about
this ברייתא braisa that we quoted, quoted about the water mill and
the incense and and the burning of the incense. So the easiest
thing to say is what we've said until now, that that whole
thing is בית הלל Beit Hillel and the one exception is the
water mill because it makes noise. But now we're still trying to
avoid the making noise problem. Making noise isn't a problem. And we're
still trying to get this whole ברייתא braisa about the water mill
to be בית שמאי. Beit Shammai. So if it's בית שמאי, Beit
Shammai, again, we're back to our question: why can you burn the
incense or why can you let the water run out into the
garden? Why are all these things allowed according to בית שמאי Beit
Shammai if בית שמאי Beit Shammai holds of שביתת כלים shvisas kelim
even if the vessel isn't doing anything? So מוגמר וגופרית מאי טעמא
שרו בית שמאי? mugmar vegofris mai ta'ama sharu Beit Shammai? Why do
they allow it? התם מנח אארעא. Hasam mancha a'ara. No,
we're not talking, there's no vessels involved. You're burning the incense without
any bowl. It's just fire and the incense. It's in the fire.
There's no vessel. That's why it's allowed. גיגית ונר וקדרה ושפוד מאי
טעמא שרו בית שמאי. Gigis vaner ukdeira ushvus mai ta'ama sharu Beit
Shammai.
So now, okay. So now we've resolved all of the texts. Let
me just review that, but but then we're going to get to
הלכה למעשה. halacha l'maaseh. What are the various texts? We have the
משנה, mishna, right, that בית שמאי Beit Shammai doesn't allow a lot
of various activities and בית הלל Beit Hillel does. So what's the
simple explanation? Either בית שמאי Beit Shammai concern is it looks like
you're involved in a מלאכה melacha on שבת, Shabbos, either you through
your vessels or through a non-Jew, whatever. It's a rabbinic concern. Or
at least the first half of the משנה mishna is a שביתת
כלים shvisas kelim concern even if the vessels are passive. That's בית
שמאי Beit Shammai issue. בית הלל Beit Hillel isn't concerned about either
of those. Fine. That's that. Then we had the ברייתא braisa that
spoke about the burning of the incense and it spoke about the
water mill. One explanation is it's בית הלל Beit Hillel and everything
is okay. The one exception is the water mill makes a lot
of noise. The next explanation is it's בית שמאי. Beit Shammai. That's
why the water mill is no good. But now you have to
explain why everything else was okay. And the answer now is all
those things just didn't involve a vessel. So if you did it
without the use of a vessel, then you're okay. That's a very
hard reading in that ברייתא, braisa, but that's what we're suggesting. Anyways,
that deals with all the texts. Now we have to ask ourselves
a question about practically. If בית שמאי Beit Shammai holds of שביתת
כלים, shvisas kelim, right, and he holds it's biblical, I mean, then
how do we allow the things that we know are מותר muttar
on שבת, Shabbos, which is what? Which is basically keeping lights on,
keeping food on the oven? How can we allow any of that
stuff? Right, you could also ask if it's a rabbinic concern that
it looks like you're doing things on שבת, Shabbos, how do we
allow these things? Let's take a look at this question.
Okay. So the גמרא Gemara says like this: גיגית ונר, gigis vaner,
if you have a barrel in which you have, apparently the way
they would make beer is right they would put, you know, barley
in a barrel and it would continue to ferment over שבת. Shabbos.
Okay. So that's something that obviously, A, you have to do with
a vessel, you can't do it on the floor.
And it would, it would happen it takes place more than a
week, it would go through שבת. Shabbos. Or simply the use of
a נר ner here doesn't mean candle, actually, it means a lamp,
an oil lamp, right, which uses a vessel, which uses a lamp.
וקדרה, ukdeira, and a
pot, stuff you food you have in your pot that continues to
cook on שבת. Shabbos. ושפוד, ushvus, or a spit if you have,
you know, stuff roasting on a spit. All these things use vessels
and we do it on שבת. Shabbos. So if it's דרבנן de-rabbanan
we can maybe make some distinction like certain things we have to
allow, whatever the distinction is, we'll make. But if it's a biblical
issue of שביתת כלים, shvisas kelim, how do you explain this? מאי
טעמא שרו בית שמאי? Mai ta'ama sharu Beit Shammai? So listen to
the answer. דאפקורי מפקירו להו. De-mafkir lu afkurei. All right, the only
way you can do this according to בית שמאי Beit Shammai is
that you make them הפקר hefker ערב שבת erev Shabbos all these
things that you are about to use and going through שבת, Shabbos,
you have to make הפקר hefker then which is, then which is,
you know, which is pretty amazing. And then come to your
house and take all your food?
Well, exactly. ערב שבת Erev Shabbos you have to make your oven
הפקר hefker and your lamps הפקר hefker and all those things הפקר
hefker if you want to continue using them on שבת. Shabbos. It
also raises questions about why couldn't you even do it in the
משנה? mishna? So maybe we only let you do it when it
was things that like really needed to be done as opposed to
things that didn't need to be done. But you can really see
the corner we're painting ourselves into. Yes, Charlie?
Same thing might apply to fermenting wine which takes a long time?
Right, same thing, presumably. Yeah.
So nobody owns any of the wine?
No, they just don't own the barrels. Because it's שביתת כלים. shvisas
kelim. You can own the food. You just can't own the vessels
that they're in. Because it's your vessels you have to let rest.
Okay.
So, מאן תנא להא דתנו רבנן, man tana l'ha detanu rabbanan, who
taught what the rabbis taught? לא תמלא אשה קדרה עססיות ותורמוסין, Lo
temalei isha kdeira asasiyos vesormasin, a woman cannot fill a pot with
these various types of legumes ותניח לתוך התנור ערב שבת עם חשכה,
vetani'ach l'toch hatannur erev Shabbos im chashecha, and put it on שבת
Shabbos into the oven because then it'll take all of שבת Shabbos
in order to cook. ואם נתנה למוצאי שבת אסור בכדי
שיעשו, Ve-im nassan l'motzei Shabbos asur b'chedei she-ya'asu, and she did it,
it's forbidden by מוצאי שבת motzei Shabbos the amount of time it
takes to do, because things that were a product of a מלאכה
melacha on שבת Shabbos you can't benefit from after שבת Shabbos until
you wait the amount of time it normally would have taken.
כיוצא בו, Kayotze bo, and in a
similar way,
לא ימלא נחתום חבית של מים, lo yemalei nachtom chavis she-mayim, a
baker should not Bagels, for bagels. Bagels, okay.
Right. And
if you do it, it's forbidden after שבת. Shabbos. So here you
see you can't put stuff on an oven ערב שבת. Erev Shabbos.
I mean, that's crazy, right? I mean, that's like, that's like what
the צדוקים Tzedukim would do. No, tell me. I know. So what
I mean, it's a whole משנה, Mishnah, we're going to see it's
a whole פרק Perek about putting stuff on an oven ערב שבת
Erev Shabbos that the גמרא Gemara says you're allowed to do. So
what's this about? I mean, with certain parameters so you shouldn't come
to stir and so on. לימא בית שמאי היא ולא בית הלל?
leima Beis Shammai hi velo Beis Hillel? Is this only בית שמאי?
Beis Shammai? נידני neidne בית שמאי, Beis Shammai, it really doesn't make
sense, but anyway, is this בית שמאי Beis Shammai ושביתת כלים? v'shvisas
keilim? It says, look at this, אפילו תימא בית הלל, afilu teima
Beis Hillel, גזירה שמא יחתה בגחלים. gezeirah shema yichateh bagichalim. We're even
בית הלל Beis Hillel we're afraid you will stir the coals. Now
this becomes we're going to have a whole פרק Perek devoted to
this, the third פרק Perek coming up not too long, which is
exactly this issue about where we get the idea of needing a
blech. And the basic reason you need a blech is because we're
concerned that you will come to adjust the flame and stir the
coals if you've got something cooking and it's not fully done when
שבת Shabbos begins. Okay, so what we are saying now here is
that the reason you're not allowed to do these things that are
mentioned here is that these things we're talking about that, you know,
the fire is there's not a blech, there's not something covering the
flame and therefore, yes, these are concerns even for בית הלל. Beis
Hillel. There's going to be a whole פרק Perek of these concerns
about not putting something uncooked on because you'll come to stir the
flames. These are concerns even בית הלל Beis Hillel has. The flip
question is, okay, but when those concerns are addressed, why is בית
שמאי Beis Shammai okay with it? What happens to שביתת כלים? shvisas
keilim? And according to this, the answer is בית שמאי Beis Shammai
would have to tell you you'd have to מפקיר mafkir your oven,
מפקיר mafkir your pots. That's the only way בית שמאי Beis Shammai
can get out of שביתת כלים, shvisas keilim, which is pretty wild.
Okay, so on the one hand, I know, it's a very... גמרא
Gemara really painted itself into a corner, which is like תוספות Tosafot
says there's a clear alternative to read this גמרא Gemara has nothing...
a משנה Mishnah has nothing to do with שביתת כלים, shvisas keilim,
has to do with a Rabbinic concern. And I don't know, this
is a particular approach that seems that wants to emphasize שביתת כלים,
shvisas keilim, but it's not the only read. So on the one
hand, if it's שביתת כלים, shvisas keilim, בית שמאי Beis Shammai would
have to say you have to מפקיר mafkir your oven and your
pots every ערב שבת. Erev Shabbos. And on the other hand, בית
הלל Beis Hillel doesn't say it's always allowed. There are issues about
covering the flame and about stirring the flame which we'll have a
whole פרק Perek devoted to. Yes.
Make your pots הפקר, hefker, do you have to take them back
in the מקוה mikvah again?
No, only if they're owned by a non-Jew, not their... not if
they're owned by nobody.
Like anyway you go ערב ראש השנה Erev Rosh Hashanah and you
say איני מודה בהם כל שבוע. eini modeh bahem kol shevua.
Right, anyway תוספות Tosafot has an interesting question because the one thing
we do פוסקן pasken is אסור assur is not שביתת כלים, shvisas
keilim, but what the תורה Torah says is אסור assur which is
שביתת בהמתו. shvisas behemo. So תוספות Tosafot says, look at תוספות Tosafot
למפקיר לא אגורי. l'mafkir lo agurei. So he says in the middle
of this... ואין לסמוך על זה להשכיר סוס לנכרי ולהפקיר. v'ein lismoch
al zeh le'haskir sus l'nochri u'l'hafkir. Rent your horse to a נכרי
nochri and he's going to use it on שבת, Shabbos, so then
comes ערב שבת Erev Shabbos you're מפקיר. mafkir. First of all, not
a good idea, he's the one holding onto the horse. הכא שאני
משום דלא אפשר בענין אחר ועוד שאינו דבר מפורסם. hacha shani mishum
d'lo efshar be'inyan acher v'od she'eino davar meforsam. Alright, so anyway
it becomes the question, can I use this way of getting out
of what is איסור דאורייתא issur d'oraisa of שביתת בהמתו? shvisas behemo?
Okay, can I use the idea of just being מפקיר mafkir it
and not telling anyone? So תוספות Tosafot sort of discusses that issue.
Anyway, let's see, back to the גמרא. Gemara. Okay. אי
הכי מוגמר וגפרית נמי לגזור? ee hachi mugmar v'gafris nami l'gezor? So
if we have a concern about stirring coals, why do we allow
you to be burning incense, whether there is a vessel, isn't a
vessel, why aren't we concerned that you'll stir the coals? התם לא
מחדי להו. hasam lo machdi lehu. There you won't stir the coals.
דאי מחדי, d'ee machdi, if you stir them, סליק בה קוטרא, salik
bei kutra, the, you know, smoke will go off וקשי להו, v'kashi
lehu, and it'll get into your clothes. Right, the whole point is
you're trying to get incense in your clothes, you don't want to
stir the coals because that's going to get smoky in your clothes,
so you're not going to do it, we're not concerned. אונין של
פשתן נמי לגזור. unin shel pishtan nami l'gezor. How about the flax?
Why do we let you put the flax in the oven according
to בית הלל? Beis Hillel? Why aren't we concerned you'll stir the
coals? התם כיון דקשי להו זיקא, hasam kivan d'kashi lehu zika, no,
because the wind exposing it to air is bad for them. ולא
מדלי ליה v'lo madlei lei and you won't open up the oven
door, you won't come to do it. So meaning we're never concerned
that you're going to intentionally stir the coals, right? We're always concerned
because if you're going to be מחלל שבת, m'chalel Shabbos, you're not
going to listen to the איסור דרבנן issur d'rabbanan either.
We're concerned that you will forget. Okay, but something that you already
naturally won't do, you know you never open up the oven door
when the flax is drying out, that's bad for the flax, so
there's not a concern. So even if you forgot it's שבת, Shabbos,
you're not going to open up the oven door. You don't do
that when you're drying out flax, so we're not concerned.
צמר ליורה לגזור. tzemer l'yora l'gezor. How about when your wool is
in the dye vat? Also over flame, let's be concerned that you'll
come to stir the coals. So אמר שמואל ביורה עקורה, amar Shmuel
b'yora akura, the vat is no longer on the flame, it's removed
from the flame, there are no coals to stir.
וניחוש שמא מגיס בה, u'neichosh shema magis bah, maybe you'll stir it.
Now, so what if you stir it? So רש"י Rashi says if
you stir it you will be over on... איסור issur of בישול.
bishul. Now first of all there's a whole question, do you have
בישול bishul by non-foodstuffs? The answer is yes you can under some
circumstances have בישול bishul by non-foodstuffs. But the other question is, can
you have biblical בישול bishul when something is not on the flame?
We generally assume that there's a problem if something is in the
vessel that was on the flame, כלי ראשון, k'li rishon, even if
it's currently not on the flame, if you stir the stuff and
you speed up the cooking, that that could be a בישול דאורייתא,
bishul d'oraisa, but there's some ראשונים rishonim that say no. Some ראשונים
rishonim say the only בישול דאורייתא bishul d'oraisa is if something is
on the flame. So what would be the concern here? So תוספות
Tosafot says there's an obvious concern. The concern here, it's not the
איסור issur of בישול, bishul, it's the איסור issur of צובע. tzoveia.
You're dying the wool. So if you stir the stuff even off
the flame, you're causing the dye to be absorbed by the wool,
and therefore that's an איסור issur of צובע. tzoveia. So why aren't
we concerned about
this sort of like ריש לקיש Reish Lakish phenomenon?
Yeah, but no, because that's absorbed, it's the definition. So anyway, so
why aren't we concerned about that? Now that you say we have
these concerns about you might come to fiddle with it, how about
you'll come to stir it? So it
says, באקורה וטוכה, b'akura u'tucha, it's off the flame and it is
sealed, like טוכה tucha means like there's some type of a plaster
around the, around the cover. So but you're not going to just
lift up the cover and stir it without thinking. So before you,
you know, so therefore you will not easily lead to stirring. והשתא
דאמר מר גזירה שמא יחתה בגחלים. V'hashta d'amar Mar gezeira shema yechateh
b'gechalim. Now, and so that's it. So now we have said even
if you get around the בית שמאי's Beit Shammai concern about שביתת
כלים shevisas keilim and they have this weird thing about מפקיר mafkir
your כלי, kli, if that's the issue it's easier to just say
it's all rabbinic. Anyway, בין בית שמאי בין בית הלל bein Beit
Shammai bein Beit Hillel there is an issue about putting things on
an oven, you might forget and stir the flame. And this as
I said is going to be the dominant issue of the whole
third פרק, perek, where you're getting here a little preview. Okay, now
that we've introduced that, one thing we've seen is it doesn't always
apply. Things that you are not, that there's an obvious disinclination to
stir regardless are things where this גזירה gezeira would not apply. And
now we're going to get some interesting exceptions to when you actually
need a בלעך. blech. Okay, now it's going to talk about dye
and whatever, it's not obvious how to translate, but here will be
something that would be obviously how to translate. So let's take a
look. It says like
this, והשתא דאמר מר, v'hashta d'amar Mar, now that we said גזירה
שמא יחתה בגחלים, gezeira shema yechateh b'gechalim, that we're concerned that you'll
stir the coals. האי קדירה חייתא שרי לאנוחה ערב שבת עם חשיכה.
Hai k'deira chayasa shari l'anucha erev Shabbos im hachashei'chah. If you have
a raw pot, meaning what's in it is raw, you can put
it on the flame ערב שבת erev Shabbos without a בלעך. blech.
Why? Because if the food is raw, it won't cook until the
entire night. There's no, you're not anxious or better stir it in
order that it'll be ready. You know it's not going to be
ready till the next morning, and you know that if you leave
it alone, it will be ready the next morning. So there's no
mo-, there's no reason why you would come to stir it. So
מאי טעמא, mai ta'ama, what's the reason? בתנורא, batannura, you can put
it in the oven. מאי טעמא? mai ta'ama? כיון דלא חזי לאורתא,
Keivan d'lo chazi l'orsa, it's not going to be anything you could
eat at night regardless. It's going to take a long time to
cook, it's raw meat. אסוחי מסח דעתיה מיניה, Asochei maseich daiteih mineih,
you just totally don't, you forget about it, like you don't, you're
not even thinking about it and you're not anxious about it. ולא
אתי לחתוי בגחלים, V'lo ati l'chtuyei b'gechalim, and you won't come to
stir. So that actually you know is a הלכה halacha that if
you actually have put up like you could put up a טשולנט
cholent totally raw ערב שבת erev Shabbos and however you פסקן pasken
about whether a crockpot needs a בלעך blech or you know need
you, what you have to do to a crockpot in order to
address בלעך blech concerns, if it's totally raw it's really you know
it's really not a problem because you're not you because you're not
afraid that you're going to come to stir.
What between raw and like a third cooked?
Right,
exactly. Now, ובשיל שפיר דמי. u'vashul shapir dami. Now if something is
already cooked, it also doesn't really need a בלעך. blech. What's the
only thing that needs a
בלעך? blech? בשיל ולא בשיל אסור. bashul v'lo bashul assur. Only something
that's not fully cooked. That's the only thing that needs a בלעך.
blech. It will cook and you will and you and it will
cook soon and you're anxious about it, and it's not yet cooked.
And there we're concerned that you're going to come to stir the
fire. So this actually is a preview of a lot of discussion
we're going to get to soon about what are the parameters of
how middle-level cooked something has to be to require a בלעך. blech.
Yes.
But some things don't take very long to cook.
Right. So the general assumption is that if you put in something
raw that will cook soon, that it does not fall into this
category and you still need a בלעך. blech. There's a רמב"ם Rambam
that actually says well you know what let's read the next line
and then I'll tell you what the רמב"ם Rambam says. But that's
the general assumption is that that case it would not have this
exception. Okay.
ושדי ביה גרמא דחייא שפיר דמי. v'shadi beh garma d'chaya shapir dami.
So you have something that's only partially cooked, it needs the fire
covered, but if you throw in a raw bone, one piece of
it, still you know one piece of meat that's going to require
six hours to cook, then you don't have to worry about it
because since that piece is going to require a long time and
it's not going to be ready for a while, you're okay. Which
raises interesting issues, right, because sometimes the טשולנט, cholent, like you know
the potatoes won't be cooked and other things will already be cooked,
and it seems like if one part of it still requires a
lot of time to cook, then it would not require a בלעך.
blech. Now the רמב"ם Rambam goes so far to say that throwing
in the one raw thing, even if it's a raw vegetable, even
if it'll cook very quickly, but it's just a היכר, heker, since
you Put it in דווקא, davka, it’s a היכר heker and therefore
it does not require covered flame. We don’t פוסקן pasken like that
רמב"ם, Rambam, okay? But there is, but actually is true that there
are a lot of cases that we, you know, that you don’t
need a בלעך blach for because things are already sufficiently cooked or
they’re, or they’re not cooked, and even if just one piece of
it is not cooked. Okay, so a lot of stuff to be
keeping in mind when we get to this in the third פרק.
perek.
Okay, now the השתא דאמרה, hashta de’amara, now that we said כל
מידי דקשיא זיקא לא מגליה, kol midi de’kashyei zika lo meigaleih, so
that was exceptions about things that you’re not, that you are not,
that you’re sort of not anxious about cooking because it’ll take the
whole night to cook. Now we also said that if you don’t
want to expose it to air, we’re not afraid that you will
stir, because obviously they’d have to get into the oven, right, in
order to, so they’d open the oven door. So those things that
we said we’re not afraid that you’ll uncover, we’ll have some other
exceptions. האי בישרא דגדייא ושריק שפיר דמי, hai bisra de’gadya veshariq shapir
dami, if you’re cooking goat meat and the oven is sealed, which
means like there’s some type of plaster around it, so you’d have
to break the seal, then you’re fine, because there’s two things that
will prevent you from opening up the door. Number one, it’s sealed,
so that will remind you. And number two is, goat meat is
presumably very susceptible to being opened to the air, that’ll hurt the
cooking. So those therefore you can cook that on ערב שבת, erev
shabbos, put it up on the oven ערב שבת, erev shabbos, we’re
not afraid you’ll open the door and stir. Due to those two
factors. Now,
דברחא דלא שריק, de’barkha delo shariq, however, if it’s ram meat and
it is not sealed, so you have neither of the good factors:
a, ram meat could be exposed to air, and b, the oven
is not sealed. So then אסור, assur, then it’s forbidden, cause you
might come forget and open it up and
stir. דגדייא ולא שריק דברחא ושריק, de’gadya velo shariq de’barkha veshariq, if
you have one of the factors, either goat meat and not sealed,
or ram meat and sealed, וברב אשי שרי vabashi de-shari רב ירמיה
מדפתי אסור, rav yirmiyah mi-difti assur,
then it’s a debate. וברב אשי vabashi says fine, I’m not afraid
you’ll open the oven and stir, and רב ירמיה rav yirmiyah says
it’s forbidden. ולרב אשי דשרי, u-le’rav ashi de’shari, according to רב אשי
rav ashi that says it’s permissible, והתנן, ve-ha-tenan, we’ll get to a
משנה mishnah very soon that’s gonna say אין צולין בשר בצל וביצה
אלא כדי שיצולו מבעוד יום. ein tzolim basar batzal u-beitzah ella kedei
she-yitzolu mi-be’od yom. You can only put up meat, onion, and egg
on a fire if it cooks from the day before, and that
presumably is even בית הלל. beis hillel. Why? Because of a concern
of stirring the fire, not concerns we said before, but the concern
of stirring the fire. So you see here it says that we
are concerned when you are roasting things, and you just said that
goat meat, right, even exposed, you know, so you’re not concerned about
these things. You know, so why is that okay? One minute.
התם בבישרא אגומרי, hasam be-bisra a-gumrei, did I skip a line? האי
בישרא דגדייא ושריק דברחא ולא שריק, hai bisra de’gadya veshariq de’barkha velo
shariq, one minute. Okay, התם דברחא ולא שריק. hasam de-barkha velo shariq.
Fine, that’s a case that I said is a problem. That’s a
case of ram meat that it’s not sealed. But any other case
that had at least one good thing going for it, either goat
meat or sealed, would be totally okay. איכא דאמרי, ika de-amri, some
say דגדייא, de’gadya, if it’s goat meat, בין שריק בין לא שריק
שפיר דמי, bein shariq bein lo shariq shapir dami, whether sealed or
not sealed, nobody’s gonna open the door when you got your goat
meat cooking, everybody says it’s okay.
דברחא נמי ושריק שפיר דמי, de-barkha nami veshariq shapir dami, as long
as it’s sealed even ram meat is okay. As long as you
got one good thing going for it, it’s okay. כי פליגי, ki
peligi, when did they debate? דברחא ולא שריק, de-barkha velo shariq, ram
meat and not sealed, nothing good is going for it, but maybe
still it’s not great to open up the door. דרב אשי שרי,
de-rav ashi shari, רב אשי rav ashi says even that’s okay, רב
ירמיה מדפתי אסור. rav yirmiyah mi-difti assur. So now if רב אשי
rav ashi says it’s permissible, you could always cook meat on a
fire ערב שבת, erev shabbos, could be totally wrong. I mean, at
least if it’s in a closed oven then because you’re afraid to
open up the oven door. So when is it ever forbidden to
have meat cooking in an oven ערב שבת, erev shabbos, raw meat?
ולרב אשי דשרי, u-le-rav ashi de-shari, והתנן אין צולין בשר בצל וביצה
אלא כדי שיצולו מבעוד יום, ve-ha-tenan ein tzolim basar batzal u-beitzah ella
kedei she-yitzolu mi-be’od yom, why do we say you can’t roast these
things, presumably we’re talking about in an oven?
According to him you’re never afraid, you’re always afraid to open the
door, so it should always be permissible.
התם בבישרא אגומרי, hasam be-bisra a-gumrei, there we’re talking about that the
meat is cooking, a slow cooking on coals. And that type of
a slow cooking on coals, that’s a type of a thing where
you’re not afraid, either you’re not afraid to open the door or
you’re very anxious that the coals are still burning, it’s not a
high fire, and that’s a case where we’re concerned you’ll stir the
fire. אמר רבינא האי קרא
חייא שפיר דמי, amar ravina hai kra’a chaya shapir dami, a raw
gourd is also something that you can cook on a fire because
it takes a long time for a raw gourd to cook, כיון
דקשיא זיקא kivein de-kashyei zika or not a long time, excuse me,
back to the air, since exposing it to air is not good
for it, כבישרא דגדייא דמי, ki bisra de-gadya dami, is like this
goat meat. So now what we have said, and we’ll end with
this today, is א, a, there’s a big question what בית שמאי’s
Beis Shammai issue is. Is it a rabbinic concern if things don’t
look good, or is it a, which seems the simpler way and
explains also the non-Jew case, or is it a case about a
biblical concern of שביתת כלים. shevisas keilim. To say that, it’s very
hard to understand how you could do anything on שבת, shabbos, like
the fire and the cooking and whatever, from ערב שבת, erev shabbos,
and you’d have to say that you were מפקיר mafkir your כלים.
keilim. That’s one thing. We’re also left with the question whether there’s
an issue about
השמעת קול. hashma’as kol. And now what we say is, even if
you don't have any of those concerns, for cooking from ערב שבת,
erev Shabbos, we know that's a series of concern. We're going to
see it in a minute in the משנה, mishna, we're going to
have a whole פרק perek devoted to it. That's a concern of
stirring the flame. And there are some exceptions to that when there's
no concern you'll stir the flame, either because it's going to take
the whole night to cook, or it's something you would not open
up the oven door. That is exceptions, and actually להלכה, lehalacha, there
are cases where you don't actually need a בלעך, blech, and we
will see more of that when we finally get
to the third פרק. perek.